Finding Aid for Women's Activism Against Sex Discrimination: The 1970 HEW Investigation of the University of Michigan records, 1999-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Women's Activism Against Sex Discrimination: The 1970 HEW Investigation of the University of Michigan records 1999-2001
University of Michigan. Institute for Research on Women and Gender.
17 audiocassettes
0.4 linear feet
2010204 Bimu 2
A 2001 research project conducted through the University of Michigan Institute for Research on Women and Gender (IRWG) on the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare's (HEW) investigation of a complaint of gender discrimination at the University of Michigan in 1970. The complaint led to amendments to Title VII and to Title IX in 1972. Files include administrative files and audio cassettes of interviews.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Received from the University of Michigan Institute for Research on Women and Gender (Donor No. 9206 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
Restricted access in part.
The Institute for Research on Women and Gender record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Interview transcripts and recordings in the Women's Activism Against Sex Discrimination: The 1970 HEW Investigation of the University of Michigan record group without signed consent forms on file are considered restricted. Transcripts and recordings for which no signed consent form is on file are noted in the inventory.
In 1970 the federal Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW) launched an investigation of the University of Michigan after Ann Arbor lawyer Jean King and the group FOCUS on Equal Employment for Women (a group founded by King to address issues of sex discrimination at the university) filed a complaint against the university with the Department of Labor. The complaint prompted hearings and resulted in a 1300 page report. Ultimately it led to amendments to Title VII legislation and contributed to Title IX in 1972.
In 2001 the University of Michigan Institute for Research on Women and Gender's (IRWG) sponsored a research project to study the 1970 HEW investigation of sex discrimination at the University of Michigan. The project report was published in 2002 as IRWG working paper number 63 Women's Activism Against Sex Discrimination: The 1970 HEW Investigation of the University of Michigan. Eric A. Stein, a graduate student, conducted the research as part of a Summer Research Internship advised by Abigail Stewart, Director of the IRWG.
Using both historical documentation and oral interviews with university faculty and staff, as well as others involved in issues of sex discrimination in the 1970s, the project was an attempt to show how the 1970 HEW investigation was important to the fight against gender discrimination both at the University of Michigan and nationally.
ARRANGEMENT
The records of the University of Michigan Institute for Research on Women and Gender's research project, "Women's Activism Against Sex Discrimination: The 1970 HEW Investigation of the University of Michigan" have been divided into two series: Project Files and Interview Audiocassettes.
Subjects:
Stein, Eric A.; Sex discrimination in employment--Michigan--Ann Arbor--20th century.; Sex discrimination in higher education--Michigan--Ann Arbor--20th century.; Women's rights--Michigan--Ann Arbor--20th century.; University of Michigan--Employees.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Research on Women and Gender.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Sex discrimination in employment--Michigan--Ann Arbor--20th century.; Sex discrimination in higher education--Michigan--Ann Arbor--20th century.; Women's rights--Michigan--Ann Arbor--20th century.; University of Michigan--Employees.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Contributors:
Carpenter, Eugenia S.; Douvan, Elizabeth Ann Malcolm, 1926-; Fleming, R. W. (Robben Wright), 1916-2010.; Hollenshead, Carol.; Kaplan, Wilfred, 1915-; King, Jean.; Larimore, Ann E.; Mills, Harriet C.; Murphy, Barbara.; Neiberg, Vicki.; Ragland-Sullivan, Ellie, 1941-; Rasmussen, Susan.; Sandler, Bernice Resnick.; Sarri, Rosemary C.; Shortridge, Kathy.; Smith, Pringle.; Soules, Aline.; Wechsler, Nancy.
Genre Terms:
Sound recordings.; Oral history.
- Project Files
  The Project Files series includes background and organizational files from the research project, including signed interview consent forms. Much of the correspondence in the series comes from Jean King, who was instrumental in pushing for the HEW investigation of the University of Michigan in 1970, and was a driving force in the IRWG research project that led to the working paper. Also included are institutional review board (IRB) approvals and correspondence, transcripts from interviews with Jean King and Bernice Sandler, and working paper revisions that include comments on the paper from Jean King. Researchers should note that signed interview consent forms are not available for all of the transcripts.
  - Project Administration
    - Institutional Review Board (IRB) (Box 1)
    - Interview Consent Forms -- Signed (Box 1)
    - Working Paper Revisions (Box 1)
    - Working Paper number 63 2002 (Box 1)
  - Interview Transcripts
    - King, Jean (Box 1)
    - Sandler, Bernice (Box 1)
      [Restricted, no release form]
  - Research Files
    - Congressionals 1970-1973 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Danbury 2000 (Box 1)
      - HEW Investigation (Box 1)
      - Other Correspondence 1999-2001 (Box 1)
    - Letters of Robin Fleming [1970-1971] (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - News Articles, 1971-2001
      - Commission for Women 1971-1996 (Box 1)
      - Equality for Women (Box 1)
      - HEW Investigation 1970-1971 (Box 1)
      - NWPC (National Women's Political Caucus) 1970-1972 (Box 1)
      - Title IX 2000-2001 (Box 1)
      - Women at UM 1970-1999 (Box 1)
  - Women's Information Network Bulletin 1972-1975 (Box 1)
- Interview Audiocassettes
  The Interview Audiocassettes series consists of seventeen audiocassette recordings of interviews conducted as part of the research for the working paper. Researchers should note that signed interview consent forms are not available for all of the recordings.
  - Anonymous PROBE Interview 8/14/2001 (Box 1)
  - Carpenter, Eugenia (Box 1)
    (see Shortridge, Kathy, Eugenia Carpenter, and Sue Rasmussen, 7/3/2001)
  - Douvan, Elizabeth 5/23/2001 (Box 1)
  - Fleming, Robben W. undated (Box 1)
  - Hollenshead, Carol 8/10/2001 (Box 1)
  - Kaplan, Wilfred 8/3/2001 (Box 1)
  - King, Jean 6/9/2001 (Box 1)
  - Larimore, Ann 6/18/2001 (Box 1)
  - Mills, Harriet and Barbara Murphy 6/27/2001 (Box 1)
  - Murphy, Barbara (see Mills, Harriet and Barbara Murphy, 6/27/2001) (Box 1)
  - Neiberg, Vicki 7/5/2001 (Box 1)
  - Ragland, Ellie 7/11/2001 (Box 1)
  - Rasmussen, Sue (Box 1)
  - Sandler, Bernice 7/17/2001 (Box 1)
  - Sarri, Rosemary 7/9/2001 (Box 1)
  - Smith, Pringle 8/1/2001 (Box 1)
  - Soules, Aline 5/15/2001 (Box 1)
  - Weschler, Nancy 7/16/2001 (Box 1)